<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Opinion | Apps and Science]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/category/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-14T12:21:49-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.appsandscience.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nikos Bentenitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five Reasons Why You See More and More People with iPhones]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/2012/01/five-reasons-why-you-see-more-and-more-people-with-iphones/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-16T09:58:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.appsandscience.com/2012/01/five-reasons-why-you-see-more-and-more-people-with-iphones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you see more and more people carrying iPhones these days? I certainly do: Everywhere I look, I see iPhones, new and old. So what do you think?</p>

<p><strong>Are there more and more people using iPhones these days?</strong></p>

<p>I set out to answer this question and here's what I found:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>43% of the smartphones sold in October/November 2011 were iPhones</em>, according to a <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/01/09/ios-marketshare-up-from-26-in-q3-to-43-in-octnov-2011/">report from TechChrunch</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><em>54% of the people surveyed who plan on buying a smartphone sometime between now and March, plan to buy an iPhone</em>, according to a <a href="http://www.changewaveresearch.com/articles/2012/smart_phones_20120109.html">report from ChangeWave Research</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>These facts along with the permanently customer-filled Apple stores, the news that <a href="http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2012/01/we-told-you-so-chinese-iphone-4s-launch-turns-into-egg-throwing-melee.ars">a riot almost broke in Beijing</a> the first day that iPhone 4S went on sale, and my constant noticing of people carrying iPhones, got me convinced: iPhones must be the most popular smartphones. That's until I read the following <a href="http://www.appleinsider.com/articles/11/12/06/kindle_fire_eats_into_ipad_sales_lead_offset_by_global_iphone_demand.html">report from Apple Insider</a>:</p>

<p><strong>Apple's share of the smartphone market is 18%, below that of Samsung at 19%.</strong></p>

<p>So?</p>

<p><strong>How come there seem to be so many iPhones despite their 18% market share?</strong></p>

<p>I am not a marketer or a consumer psychologist, but here are five reasons why you may notice more and more people with iPhones:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>There's only one iPhone but hundreds of Android phones</strong>: Because there is only one iPhone, but hundreds of Samsung phones, it is easier to recognize an iPhone. This behavior might be related to what social theorist Barry Schwartz calls <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060005696/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=appsandscienc-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0060005696">the paradox of choice</a>: more choices are not necessarily better.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Apple aggressively advertises its products</strong>: When Apple announces a new device, everybody knows about it: the media, the bloggers, everybody. So after such a barrage of information, when you see a new Apple device, you recognize it.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Apple aggressively places its products in movies</strong>: Apple products are aggressively placed in popular movies, about 30% of them in 2010, <a href="http://www.appleinsider.com/articles/11/02/22/apple_products_appeared_in_30_of_all_top_movies_in_2010.html">according to Apple Insider</a>. Apple products are placed more frequently in movies than those of Nike or Ford.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The iPhone 4S was introduced in October</strong>: Happy owners of the new iPhone 4S were busy playing with their device, effectively displaying it more frequently to friends and strangers.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The iPhone has become a very popular camera</strong>: At least for Flickr users, the iPhone is the most popular camera. And there is no easier way for people to display their iPhones than when they take it out to take a picture, especially during the holiday season.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>So what do you think? <strong>How do you explain that there seem to be so many iPhones around despite their 18% market share?</strong> Share your opinion in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
