<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tiggzi | Apps and Science]]></title>
  <link href="http://appsandscience.github.com/blog/categories/tiggzi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://appsandscience.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-07T20:17:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://appsandscience.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nikos Bentenitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating an iPhone application without coding: The Tiggzi solution]]></title>
    <link href="http://appsandscience.github.com/creating-an-iphone-application-without-coding-the-tiggzi-solution/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-06T02:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://appsandscience.github.com/creating-an-iphone-application-without-coding-the-tiggzi-solution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few weeks I have been experimenting with various tools that one can use to develop an iPhone/iPad application, without the need to program in Objective-C. In a previous blog post <a href="http://www.appsandscience.com/getting-started-on-app-development-with-a-little-help-from-canappi/">I described Canappi</a>, a tool that uses a specialized language, MDSL, to generate Objective-C code. In this post, I will describe <a href="http://www.tiggzi.com">Tiggzi</a>, a web service that creates native code for iPhone and Android applications using a coding-free graphical user interface. I will first describe the advantages and disadvantages of Tiggzi, and I will then share with you my recommendation about the service.</p>

<h3>Advantages</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Tiggzi does not require any coding. Dragging and dropping widgets on a canvas is the only thing that is required from a user of Tiggzi.</p></li>
<li><p>The applications created by Tiggzi can be be run on iPhones and iPads as well as on Android devices and mobile-phone browsers.</p></li>
<li><p>Creating application screens is straightforward in Tiggzi, and transitioning between those screens is very easy. Also, each button, label, image can navigate to a new screen by selecting the appropriate settings.</p></li>
<li><p>It is very easy for a user to define and connect to REST services. Importing data using JSON, for instance, is very easy and the results of the queries can be easily included in a table view. This common task is handled very well in Tiggzi and a tutorial on Tiggzi's website explains the process step-by-step.</p></li>
<li><p>The source code that Tiggzi generates is a collection of HTML and CSS files bundled with PhoneGap. That code can be edited in Apple's XCode.</p></li>
<li><p>The Tiggzi website contains several well-presented tutorials that describe the creation of data-driven applications, which are common in business.</p></li>
<li><p>Tiggzi makes it very easy to share an application with testers and clients by supplying a custom URL with the HTML/CSS source code of the application. In the paid version, Tiggzi allows team members to collaborative on the creation of the applications.</p></li>
<li><p>For Android applications Tiggzi provides an app that runs the code generated by Tiggzi natively on the phone, even before the application is launched and submitted in the Android marketplace.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Despite its great number of advantages, Tiggzi may not be the platform that some developers may choose. That's because the service has a few disadvantages.</p>

<h3>Disadvantages</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Tiggzi does not generate native GUI elements, at least for the iPhone that I tested it with. As a result, applications do not feel native. In addition, I had several problems using a table view, a common element in the business applications that I am interested in creating.</p></li>
<li><p>The service is not free. Tiggzi has several subscription levels but the free version provides a great feel for the service. (The free tier is currently limited to one project and on constructing three screens.)</p></li>
<li><p>A developer depends on the web-interface to create the application. That interface may change as a function of time. Although this might not be a disadvantage, provided that the interface improves.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Although Tiggzi has a lot of advantages, the lack of non-native GUI elements, might stop developers from using the service to create polished applications. However, Tiggzi provides a simple interface for creating apps and for sharing working prototypes with testers and clients.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
