<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Canappi | Apps and Science]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/category/canappi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-14T14:13:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.appsandscience.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nikos Bentenitis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started on App Development with a Little Help from Canappi]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.appsandscience.com/2012/01/getting-started-on-app-development-with-a-little-help-from-canappi/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-23T02:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.appsandscience.com/2012/01/getting-started-on-app-development-with-a-little-help-from-canappi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/canappi.png" width="300" height="300" title="Canappi iPhone DSL" alt="Canappi iPhone DSL"></p>

<p>Developing simple data-driven apps for the iPhone is not simple. Objective-C, the native language of the iPhone, is very difficult, and accomplishing simple tasks can be quite complicated.</p>

<p>I realized that when I tried to created a simple menu driven application that catalogs all the Chemistry apps on the Apple store. Just a bit of background: Depending on how you choose to classify the available Chemistry apps, they belong to the following categories:</p>

<ol>
<li>Exam preparation</li>
<li>Chemistry-related calculators</li>
<li>Books</li>
<li>Reference works</li>
<li>Games</li>
</ol>


<p>These categories can be subdivided into additional categories, but for the purposes of this post, let's stick with those.</p>

<p>Now imagine an iPhone application that has a tab bar at the bottom with two tabs: One is called "Featured" and the other one is called "Categories." See the screenshot below. When you tap on one of the categories you can see a list of related apps, "App 1," "App 2," etc. When you tap on the "Featured" tab you can see a list of featured apps, "Featured App 1," "Featured App 2," etc.</p>

<p>When I started with iPhone development, I thought that creating such a simple app should be very easy. Well, I was in for a surprise: it was not easy at all. Mostly because Objective-C is not an easy language to program.</p>

<p>But recently I found a code generation platform that made developing such a simple application, well simple. The platform is called <a href="http://www.canappi.com">Canappi</a>. In order to create an app in Canappi you need to use a specialized language called MDSL. Using MDSL one can easily create application menus, views, and layouts.</p>

<p>The MDSL code below demonstrates how straightforward it can be to create the iPhone app shown above.</p>

<p>First, you need to identify your app</p>

<pre><code>package com.yourname.chemapps ;
</code></pre>

<p>Second, you need to create three layouts. One for the app list, one for the featured apps list and one for the list of categories.</p>

<p>For the app list layout, first you create a table that is going to be used as menu and you populate it with menu items. When each of the menu items is tapped, the application navigates to a screen with the details of the selected app.</p>

<pre><code>layout appsLayout {
    table buttonMenu as menu {
        menuitem 'App 1' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; }
        menuitem 'App 2' {action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; }
        menuitem 'App 3' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; }
        menuitem 'App 4' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; }
        menuitem 'App 5' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView; }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The layout for the featured applications is the same as that for the app list, apart from the titles of the menu items.</p>

<pre><code>layout featuredLayout {
    table buttonMenu as menu {
        menuitem 'Featured App 1' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; }
        menuitem 'Featured App 2' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; } menuitem 'Featured App 3' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; } menuitem 'Featured App 4' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; } menuitem 'Featured App 5' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to detailView ; } } }
</code></pre>

<p>Similarly for the layout of the various categories, but the target of each row is different: it's the examPrepView when the "Exam Prep" option is selected, etc.</p>

<pre><code>layout categoriesLayout {
    table buttonMenu as menu {
        menuitem 'Exam prep' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to examPrepView ; }
        menuitem 'Calculators' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to calculatorsView ; }
        menuitem 'Books' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to booksView ; }
        menuitem 'Reference' { action displayGradientButtons navigate to referenceView ; }
        menuitem 'Fun' {action displayGradientButtons navigate to funView ; }
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>Third, you need to create views for each category, the apps list, the details list, the categories list and the featured list</p>

<pre><code>view examPrepView 'ExamPrep' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view calculatorsView 'Calculators' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view booksView 'Books' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view referenceView 'Reference' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view funView 'Fun' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view appsView 'Apps' {
    controls {
        layout appsLayout ;
    }
}

view detailView 'Details' {
// Empty view
}

view categoriesView 'Categories' {
    controls {
        layout categoriesLayout ;
    }
}

view featuredView 'Featured' {
    controls {
        layout featuredLayout ;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Fourth, you need to look at the main window of the application, add a navigation bar, declare the view from which the application will start, as well as the items in the tab-bar menu.</p>

<pre><code>main chemapps {
    navigationBar;
    start categoriesView ;
    menu { categoriesView , featuredView}
}
</code></pre>

<p>And that's it. If you upload this file to Canappi's code generator, you will receive a zip file with the XCode project file and source code for your application (in addition to the source code for the Android platform.) You can open those files in XCode, and run the compiled application.</p>

<p>Several notes are in order:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>MDSL files can be edited in Eclipse, the widely used integrated development environment, as described on Canappi's website.</p></li>
<li><p>The generation of XCode files is done only by uploading an MDSL file to canappi.com</p></li>
<li><p>You have to become a member of the Canappi website in order to have access to the servers at canappi.com.</p></li>
<li><p>The use of Canappi's servers is currently free, but the developer has plans to charge for their use.</p></li>
<li><p>If you create an interface in XCode's interface builder, you can use a tool in canappi.com to create an MDSL file that you can then edit. At Canappi.com you can also import an interface created in Balsamiq, and export it to an MDSL file.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Canappi provides an alternative to mobile development if you are not very comfortable with Objective-C. With only little effort, simple applications can be easily created, not only for the iPhone but for Android too.</p>

<p>Read more about the project by visiting <a href="http://www.canappi.com">www.canappi.com</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
